Robert Wilden Neeser collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Robert Wilden Neeser collection
1798-1909
MS 366
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
20
(16 boxes, 1 folio)
The major part of this collection is made up of 58 volumes of logbooks for fifty-one British warships (1808-1840). The remainder of the collection consists of research material for his study of the history of the United States Navy (published 1909). Included are a list of vessels (1775-1907), a list of logbooks (1800-1907) and copies of letters from the archives of the United States Navy (1798-1842). Also included is a volume of records kept ca. 1870 by Horace A. Blanchard concerning the United States frigate Sabine.
Neeser, Robert Wilden, 1884-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robert W. Neeser.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Born July 16, 1884, Seabright, NJ; missing since September 30, 1940, Lyons, France (later presumed dead).
Father, John Caspar Neeser, partner Isehn, Neeser & Company, dry goods, New York City, son of Hans Caspar and Anna (Ruf) Neeser Mother, Josephine Clementine (Wilden) Neeser; daughter of Jean Frederic Joseph and Marie Ursole Louise (Proutier) Wilden.
The Browning School Second dispute appointment Junior year, first dispute appointment, George Washington Egleston Historical Prize, and John Addison Porter Prize Senior year; Freshman Crew, member The Pundits.
Studied government archives on naval history Washington, DC, 1906-7; with Charles Scribner's Sons, New York City, 1907-8, M A. Yale 1909, studied American and foreign naval history and accompanied United States naval forces on cruises 1909- 14, American representative "Oeuvre Mon Soldat 1915" (society to aid correspondence with French soldiers at the front 1915-18; awarded Medaille de la Reconnaissance Franchise 1918) and editor. Lettres de Mon Soldat (1916), volunteer assistant American naval attache, Pans, 1917-18; commissioned First Lieutenant, U.S Infantry, June 15, 1918; attached to Intelligence Section, Services of Supply, American Expeditionary Forces, and served as assistant to Chief of Operations, Second Section, General Staff, France, until discharge May 12, 1919; liaison officer historical section American naval attache, Pans, 1919-21; manager Western Union Telegraph Company, Paris, 1921-23; with National City Bank of New York, Paris, 1923-40, awarded French Academic palms 1919 and chevalier of Legion of Honor 1927; did research work at Bibhotheque Nationale, Pans; author: Statistical and Chronological History of the United States Navy; A Landsman's Log; Our Navy and the Next War; Our Many- Sided Navy, Ship Names of the United States Navy, translator: Rostand's Chantecler, Claudel Paul's Ute D'or, and The City; editor: American Naval Songs and Ballads, member Squadron A, New York National Guard, secretary-treasurer Naval History Society 1909-16, secretary Yale Alumni Association in France 1932-36; associate member Academie de Marine, member U S. Naval Institute (Annapolis), American Historical Association, and Navy committee of National Security League, and Roman Catholic church.
Married May 15, 1919, in Paris, Susanne, daughter of General Emile Eugene Belin. Children: Jean Stanislas (deceased); Odilc Elvine de Borde; Beatrice; Robert Martial (grad ecole Navale), and Marie-Jose (deceased).
Presumed dead after being missing since September 30, 1940. Survived by wife, two daughters, one son, and two sisters, Miss Elvme Louise Neeser of New York City, and Madame Charles Lestelle of Paris.
Source: Yale Obituary Record, 1948-1949, pages 176-177.
Scope and Contents
The major part of this collection is made up of 58 volumes of logbooks for fifty-one British warships (1808-1840). The remainder of the collection consists of research material for his study of the history of the United States Navy (published 1909). Included are a list of vessels (1775-1907), a list of logbooks (1800-1907) and copies of letters from the archives of the United States Navy (1798-1842). Also included is a volume of records kept ca. 1870 by Horace A. Blanchard concerning the United States frigate Sabine.
Arrangement
Logbooks arranged alphabetically by ship.
Europe; Great Britain; Logbooks; Blanchard, Horace A., d. 1876; Neeser, Robert Wilden, 1884-; Great Britain. Royal Navy -- History; United States. Navy ( History)
- Original accession
  - Log Books of British war ships, 1808-1840
    - Alacrity, 1808-1810 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Alceste, 1809-1812 (Box 1)
    - Argus, 1809-1810 (Box 1)
    - Barracout, 1810 (Box 1)
    - Barf1eur, 1812-1813 (Box 1)
    - Beaver, 1812-1815 (Box 2)
    - Centinel, 1810-1811 (Box 2)
    - Chiffonne, 1808-1811 (Box 2)
    - Conflict, 1818-1809 (Box 2)
    - Constant, 1808-1811 (Box 2)
    - Constant, 1810-1811 (Box 2)
    - Cornwallis, 1808-1837 (Box 3)
    - Crane, 1813-1814 (Box 3)
    - Cruizer, 1809-1812 (Box 3)
    - Eclipse, 1836 (Box 3)
    - Edgar, 1807-1816 (Box 3)
    - Edgar, 1809-1810 (Box 4)
    - Hermes, 1832 (Box 4)
    - Imperieus, 1809-1812 (Box 4)
    - Iphigenia, 1820-1821 (Box 4)
    - Iphigenia, 1818-1822 (Box 5)
    - Lightning, 1827-1828 (Box 5)
    - Lion, 1823-1824 (Box 5)
    - Liverpool, 1818-1822 (Box 5)
    - Madagascer, 1832 (Box 5)
    - Maidstone, 1829-1831 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Medina, 1824-1825 (Box 5)
    - M0nkey, 1827-1830 (Box 6)
    - Nimrod, 1824-1833 (Box 6)
    - Phoebe, 1808-1813 (Box 6)
    - Pickle, 1827-1828 (Box 7)
    - Piedmontaise, 1811-1812 (Box 7)
    - Prospera, 1809-1813 (Box 7)
    - Prospero, 1809-1811 (Box 7)
    - Raleigh, 1808-1814 (Box 7)
    - Raleigh, 1830-1834 (Box 8)
    - Ranger, 1808-1813 (Box 8)
    - Rhadarnanthus, 1833-1840 (Box 8)
    - Rodney, 1810-1811 (Box 8)
    - Rover, 1808-1809 (Box 9)
    - Rover, 1832-1838 (Box 9)
    - San Josef, 1832-835 (Box 9)
    - San Josef, 1809-1813 (Box 10)
    - Sapphire, 1813-1836 (Box 10)
    - Sea Horse, 1807-1814 (Box 10)
    - Snake, 1808-1836 (Box 11)
    - Standard, 1809-1812 (Box 11)
    - Talavera, 1824-1831 (Box 11)
    - Tarter, 1818-1823 (Box 12)
    - Tribune, 1834-1839 (Box 12)
    - Tyrian, 1826-1828 (Box 12)
    - Unicorn, 1809-1814 (Box 13)
    - Vengeance, 1808-1809 (Box 13)
    - Vengeur, 1810-1815 (Box 13)
    - Volage, 1812 (Box 13)
    - Warrior, 1815 (Box 14)
    - Zealous, 1808-1814 (Box 14)
    - Zenobia, 1809-1814 (Box 14)
  - Other Volumes
    - Complete list of the log books on file in the Bureau of Navigation, Dept. of the Navy, Washington, D. C., 1800-1907 Typescript (Box 1)
    - Complete list of the vessels of the u.s. Navy, 1775-1907, Typescript (bound with above). (Box 1)
    - List of Unofficial Publications consulted and referred to in the compilation of a statistical and chronological history of the U.S. Navy. Typescript, 1907 (Box 16)
    - A Statistical and Chronological History of the United States Navy, from the Commencement to the present day. Compiled from the most reliable sources [crossed out and written above: Manuscript and official sources] by Robert Hilden Neeser, 1904-1906. With items, laid in Published by Macmillan, New York, 1909 (Box 17)
    - The Trent Affair, by "Nauphilos." Typescript, 1906. 193p. John Addison Porter prize in American-history, Yale University, 1906 [see RU 331, ACCN 19ND-A-381, Box 8, Folder 69]
    - Watch, quarter &station bill, U.S. Frigate "Sabine." Horace A. Blanchard, Midn. U.S.N. 1 vol, 1870? (Box 16)
    - U.S. Navy Dept. Archives. Executive letters ... 1798-1842, typewritten for R. W. Neeser. Washington, 3v., 1900 (Box 15)